Guide to the Walter J. P. Curley Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Walter J. P. Curley papers
1918-2014
MS 2009
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
12.25
(24 boxes)
The papers document Walter J. P. Curley's public service career and experiences abroad, in particular his service in the United States Marine Corps in the Pacific and China during World War II and his work as United States ambassador to Ireland (1975-1977) and France (1989-1993). The papers consist of correspondence, public service papers, speeches, writings, and photographs.
Curley, Walter J. P., 1922-2016
Scope and Contents
The papers document Walter J. P. Curley's public service career and experiences abroad, in particular his service in the United States Marine Corps in the Pacific and China during World War II and his work as United States ambassador to Ireland (1975-1977) and France (1989-1993). The papers consist of correspondence, public service papers, speeches, writings, and photographs.
Curley's time in the Marines is documented in detail by letters he wrote to his parents about his experiences as an infantry officer in the Iwo Jima campaign and as a general's aide in Okinawa and northern China. Most of these letters have been published in Walter J. P. Curley, Letters from the Pacific, 1943-1946, but several have remained unpublished.
The materials concerning his Ireland ambassadorship primarily document the routine operations of the embassy including invitations, visitors, and assistance provided to Americans in Ireland. The Ireland papers include a file list which inventories all of Curley's office files, but not all of these files were included in this collection and archivists have simplified the organization of the remaining files to ease researcher access.
The correspondence and public service files regarding his ambassadorship in France contain less material concerning routine embassy operations and more material concerning U.S.-France relations, but the latter is still quite limited. Much of the correspondence is personal in nature but includes a small amount of correspondence with George H. W. Bush, James Baker, and French leaders which provides some insight into policy. Among the public service files, there are notes Curley wrote of a meeting between French president François Mitterrand and American vice president Dick Cheney. The materials concerning Curley's ambassadorship in France came to the archives with little original order.
The papers also provide insight into the role of and the controversies over politically-appointed ambassadors including a draft paper on the topic, a file concerning the Reagan-Bush presidential campaign, and correspondence from Curley's ambassadorships.
The speech files probably provide the best overview of his work as ambassador to Ireland and France in these papers. His writings include extensive memoir and autobiographical works covering virtually all aspects of his life from childhood.
The papers contain little from his career in business and venture capital.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research except for box 15 which is restricted until the materials are declassified.
Biographical / Historical
Walter J. P. Curley was a venture capitalist who served as U.S. ambassador to Ireland from 1975 to 1977 and to France from 1989 to 1993. He was born in Pittsburgh on September 17, 1922. He graduated from Yale College in 1943. During World War II, he served as a Marine Corps officer at Iwo Jima, Okinawa, and in northern China. Curley died on June 2, 2016 in New York, New York.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ambassador Walter J. P. Curley, 2014.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, Circa 1918-2001. II. Public Service Papers, 1944-circa 2014. III. Speeches, 1967-2006. IV. Writings, Circa 1985-circa 1997. V. Photographs, 1943-1993.
World War, 1939-1945; United States -- Foreign relations -- France; United States -- Foreign relations -- Ireland; Curley, Walter J. P., 1922-2016; Curley, Walter J. P., 1922-2016
- Correspondence, Circa 1918-2001; Series I
  - General
    - Bush, George H. W. and family, 1996-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bush, George W., 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Europe, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - India, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ireland, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letter from Walter J. Curley (father) to Marguerite Curley [?], Circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Post-ambassadorships, 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Snowden, 1939, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Yale, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - United States Marine Corps
    - General
      - General, 1945-02 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - General, 1945-03-06-1945-03-18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - General, 1945-03-21-1945-03-29 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - General, 1945-09-17-1946-01-15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence to Walter and Marguerite Curley from family friends about Marine Corps letters, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters from the Pacific, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ambassador to Ireland
    - A, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - B, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - C, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Curley, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - D, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - E, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - F, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Family correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - G, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - I, J, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - K, L, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - K, L, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - M, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Mc, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - N, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - O, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - P, Q, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - R, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - S, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - T, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - X, Y, Z, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Congratulatory mail, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - Ambassador to France, 1989-1993 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
- Public service papers, 1944-circa 2014; Series II
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials in box 15 are restricted until declassified by the federal government.
  - General
    - A Conversation with Ambassador Walter Curley, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Biographical information, Circa 2014 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Oral history interview of Walter J. P. Curley, National WWII Museum, 2009 (Box 25–27)
      Unprocessed electronic record. Closed until processed.
    - Personal resume, Circa 1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Reagan-Bush campaign and the Irish-American electorate, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - United States Marine Corps
    - Cerificates and citations, 1943-1945 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Handbooks, regulations, and Japanese language materials, 1944-1945 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Japan and the Japanese, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Japanese lessons, Circa 1944-circa 1946 (Box 6, Folder 8-13)
    - Japanese slide ruler, Undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Marine's Handbook, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Personal orders, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Stockade forms and maps in Japanese, Circa 1945 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Stockade sign, Circa 1945 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Stockade sketches-Iwo Jima, Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - World War II letter by unidentified author, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ambassador to Ireland
    - General, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
    - Art in the embassies, 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Articles, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Automobile, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Banks, 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Bicentennial, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Biographical data, 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Biographical data on Irish personalities, 1974-1977 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Restricted until declassified by the federal government.
    - Briefing, 1973-1975 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Chief of Mission briefing book, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Chronological files
      - 1975-06-27-1975-09-15 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - 1975-09-18-1975-10-31 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - 1975-11 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - 1975-12 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - 1976-01 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - 1976-02 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - 1976-03 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - 1976-04 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - 1976-05 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - 1976-06 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - 1976-07 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - 1976-08 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - 1976-09 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - 1976-10 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - 1976-11 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - 1976-12 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - 1977-01 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - 1977-02 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - 1977-03 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - 1977-04 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Clubs, 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Congratulations, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Credentials, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Curley family, 1974-1977 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - European Chiefs of Mission meeting briefing, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - File list, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Guest lists, 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
    - Hospitalization, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Insurance, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Invitations, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Memorandum of conversation with Garret FitzGerald, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Monarchs in Waiting, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Northern Ireland, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Northern Ireland background material, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Northern Ireland conflict, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Notes on Northern Ireland, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Official correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Party invitees, 1974-1977 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
    - Personnel, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Protocol, 1969-1975 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Receipts, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Reports and background materials on Ireland, 1973-1975 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Residence, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Resignation [1 of 2], 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Resignation [2 of 2], 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Resignation letter, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Rossyvera, 1965, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Schedules
      - 1975 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - 1976 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - 1977 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Section chiefs briefing, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Shooting and fishing, 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Spaulding, Vivian, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Speaking engagements/invitations, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Trips
      - Brussels, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Cork, 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Future, reference, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Future, reference, 1975-1977 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
      - Galway/Inisboffin, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Kilkenny, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - London, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - United States of America, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Vestal, A. A., 1975-1977 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Visit of Russell Train, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Visitors, 1975-1976 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Ambassador to France
    - Appointment book, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Bulgaria/Hungary restoration, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Comprehensive settlement of the Cambodia conflict, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Confirmation hearing, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Congressional delegations, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Farmers protest, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Franco-American organizations, 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Franco-Irish organizations, 1989-1993 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Guest lists, 1993-02-04 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Honorary committees, 1979, 1989-1992 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Inspector's evaluation report of Walter J. P. Curley, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Letter to James A. Baker III, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Martinique summit, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Meeting of Class I Post ambassadors, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Meeting of President Bush and President Mitterrand, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Memoranda, 1989-circa 1993 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Memoranda, 1989-1992 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Memoranda of conversation, 1990-1992 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Messages, 1990-1993 (Box 15, Folder 13-14)
    - Mission, program plan, fiscal years 1993-1997, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Mitterrand, François, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Notes, 1989-circa 1993 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Press release on President Bush's 1991 budget, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Tourism, exports, and investments, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Visit of Roland Dumas to Washington, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Speeches, 1967-2006; Series III
  - 1967 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - 1974 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - 1974-1976 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - 1975-1977 (Box 16, Folder 4-7)
  - 1976 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - 1977 (Box 16, Folder 9-10)
  - 1978 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - 1978-1980 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - 1989-1990 (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
  - 1989-1993 (Box 17, Folder 4-8)
  - 1990 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
  - 1990-1993 (Box 18, Folder 4-7)
  - 1990-1993 (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
  - Circa 1990-circa 1993 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - 1993 (Box 19, Folder 5-9)
  - 1993-2006 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - 1994 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - 1995 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - 1996 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - 1999 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - 2001 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Oral history interview, National World War II Museum, Circa 2009
    Closed until processed.
  - Undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Writings, Circa 1985-circa 1997; Series IV
  - Draft paper on opposition to non-career ambassadorships, Circa 1985 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Draft forewords to "Mister Wu and Other Shadows", 1992-1993 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - "How Long Does a Tattoo Last? An American Life East and West of Suez", 2014
  - "Marine Corps Diary" draft, Undated (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
  - Memoir drafts, Circa 1990 (Box 21, Folder 5-9)
  - Memoir manuscripts on his childhood, Undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - "Stories for James", Circa 1997 (Box 21, Folder 11-12)
  - "Stories for James", Circa 1997 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Yale class of 1944 memoir, 1974 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Yale University and other early writings, Undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1943-1993; Series V
  - General
    - Prints, Undated (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
    - Negatives, Undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Ambassador to France, 1989-circa 1993 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Ambassador to Ireland, Circa 1975-circa 1977 (Box 23, Folder 5-6)
  - Marine Corps, 1943 (Box 23, Folder 7)